{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This location is the setting of an “Outdoor Scene” often paired with “The Pond” and “Halloween” by Charles Ives. One section of this region was dedicated on October 9, 1985, is a short walk from the Dakota apartment complex, and features a tile mosaic around the word “Imagine.” A 1981 benefit concert to revive this location brought 500,000 people to it to listen to “Mrs. Robinson” and other Simon and Garfunkel songs. The Strawberry Fields memorial to John Lennon is located in, for ten points, what landmark green space designed by Frederick Law Olmstead in Manhattan?",
      "answer": [
        "Central Park",
        "Central Park in the Dark"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man’s step-grandfather, White Man Runs Him, served as a scout for Custer’s forces prior to the Battle of the Little Bighorn. This man published a book on buffalo jump techniques and, while serving in World War II, managed to steal 50 horses belonging to the SS, an exploit that helped this 2009 recipient of the Presidential Medal of Freedom become a War Chief. For ten points, name this Plains Indians War Chief of the Crow nation who died in 2016 at the age of 102.",
      "answer": "Joseph Medicine Crow High Bird"
    },
    {
      "question": "The scope of this amendment was expanded by a case filed against a worker who was paid an advance of $15 by the Riverside Company, then quit shortly thereafter. James Mitchell Ashley introduced a bill that was rolled into this amendment. The aforementioned Bailey v. Alabama strengthened this amendment, whose purpose was undermined by the rise of sharecropping as a replacement for indentured servitude. For ten points, name this civil rights amendment, ratified in 1865, that abolished slavery.",
      "answer": "13th Amendment"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man “placed his dithyrambs in the hands of the poet of Isoline” in a letter signed “Dionysus;” that letter is one of his Wahnzettel [vahn-zettel], or Madness Letters. According to legend, after this man witnessed a horse being flogged in Turin, he ran to protect it and collapsed at its side. After this man’s death, his sister Elizabeth compiled and published the unfinished The Will to Power, which describes the problem of nihilism, a philosophy that this thinker’s earlier works explained was the end result of the death of God. For ten points, name this German philosopher who wrote The Gay Science.",
      "answer": "Friedrich Nietzsche"
    },
    {
      "question": "One of this man’s works ends with a prayer asking whether this is the “fullness of Joy” that the Lord promises. That work by this man opens with an “exhortation of the mind to the contemplation of God,” who this man defined as a “being greater than which none can be conceived” in what is now considered the original ontological argument for God’s existence. The Proslogion was written by, for ten points, what early 12th century Archbishop of Canterbury who is often considered the founder of Scholasticism?",
      "answer": "Saint Anselm of Canterbury"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man built a fort on Aethelney hill after being surprised in an attack on Chippenham. While hiding in the Somerset marshes, this man is said to have been scolded for letting a bunch of cakes burn; that story was related by his biographer, Bishop Asser. This ruler ordered a fyrd to muster on Whitsuntide at Egbert’s Stone. This victor of the Battle of Ashdown fortified his country with burhs, and successfully defended his kingdom against the Great Heathen Army. For ten points, name this ruler, enemy of Guthrum of Mercia and king of Wessex, known as “the Great.”",
      "answer": "Alfred the Great"
    },
    {
      "question": "Jean-Jacque Maimoni was killed by friendly fire in this event. In carrying out this event, Wilfred Bose protested that he was not a Nazi. During this event, Dora Bloch was allowed to leave due to illness, then was killed anyway. Jonathan Netanyahu was the IDF’s only fatality in this event; others killed included two members of the Popular Front for the Liberation of Palestine, who had hijacked Air France Flight 139. For ten points, name this July 4, 1976 counter-terrorism operation in which over 100 hostages were rescued from an airport in Uganda.",
      "answer": [
        "Entebbe raid",
        "Operation Entebbe",
        "Operation Thunderbolt"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Sebastiano Venier rose to prominence after this battle, where one side lost a force of irreplaceable composite archers. A bronze sculpture of Neptune was crafted to bear similarities to one admiral in this battle, which was preceded by the siege of Famagusta. The winning side formed wings flanking the flagship Real [ray-AHL]. Andrea Doria and Miguel Cervantes fought in this battle, whose winning side was led by Don Juan of Austria. For ten points, name this 1571 naval victory for the Holy League over the Ottoman Empire.",
      "answer": "Battle of Lepanto"
    },
    {
      "question": "In this territory, Manuel Rojas led the Grito de Lares uprising against Spanish rule. In 1950, Blanca Canales burned a post office in Jayuya during an anti-American uprising. Oscar Collazo and Griselio Torresola attempted to kill President Truman in an effort to raise awareness of this territory’s independence movement. For ten points, name this American commonwealth where, in 2012, only 5% of citizens voted for becoming an independent country with capital San Juan, instead suggesting that it become the 51st state.",
      "answer": "Puerto Rico"
    },
    {
      "question": "A building in this city designed by Pierre Cardin has been derided for looking like an “illuminated mushroom.” This city is home to the Palace of Light and the Palazzo Dario, which was painted by Claude Monet. To protect trade secrets, this city forbade glassmakers on its island of Murano from leaving. Canaletto depicted this city in his painting Return of Bucentaure, Ascension Day and his many depictions of its Canalasso. For ten points, name this Italian city built precariously on the Mediterranean, where gondolas navigate its many canals.",
      "answer": "Venice"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Juan de Betanzos wrote a narrative history of this conflict. The Canari people switched sides during this conflict, choosing to follow the loser of this war. The decisive battle in this conflict was the Battle of Quipaipan. The loyal generals Ruminahui and Quizquiz supported the eventual winner of this conflict, who was captured at the Battle of Cajamarca shortly after this war ended. For ten points, name this war fought over a throne left vacant by the death of Huayna Capac, which ended when Huascar defeated was by his half-brother Atahualpa.",
        "answer": [
          "Incan Civil War",
          "War of the Incan Succession",
          "War of the Two Brothers"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "After he was captured by Pizarro, Atahualpa was ransomed for what? Description acceptable; we’re not looking for a number.",
        "answer": [
          "a room full of gold and/or silver",
          "Ransom Room"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man scored a decisive victory against the Macromanni after forming a pincer with Gaius Saturninus. His invasion of Armenia allowed for the return of the Roman standards lost at Carrhae. This man was forced to divorce Vipsania and marry Julia the Elder; Tacitus notes that his hatred of his wife may have led him to retire to Rhodes. He met his end in Capri when he was smothered by the prefect Macro, to be succeeded by a man whom this emperor described as a “viper in Rome’s bosom.” For ten points, name this son of Livia Drusilla who was succeeded as Roman emperor by Caligula.",
        "answer": "Tiberius Claudius Nero"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This powerful Praetorian and friend of Tiberius was put to death for attempting to plot with Livilla against Tiberius. He had earlier risen to power after the death of Drusus.",
        "answer": "Lucius Aelius Seianus or Sejanus"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The incumbent president called one candidate in this election year “a stooge for Wall Street.” Jacqueline Cochran’s Serenade film inspired this election’s eventual winner, who Henry Cabot Lodge, Jr. entered into the New Hampshire primary without his permission, where he defeated an Ohio senator. An advertisement during this election repeated the refrain “You like Ike, I like Ike, everybody likes Ike.” For ten points, name this election, which was the first time that Adlai E. Stevenson was defeated in a landslide by Dwight D. Eisenhower.",
        "answer": "Election of 1952"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Eisenhower defeated this Ohio senator for the Republican nomination. He co-sponsored a 1947 anti-union law along with Fred Hartley.",
        "answer": "Robert Alphonso Taft"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The book A Russian Journal was illustrated with this man’s photos. A photo taken by this man in the Sicilian village of Sperlinga shows an elderly peasant pointing towards where German troops had gone to an American soldier. One of this man’s photos shows an American soldier struggling in the surf during the D-Day landings, one of his blurry “Magnificent Eleven” photos. Though its authenticity is debated, this man’s most famous photo shows the death of Federico Borrell Garcia as his outstretched right hand drops his rifle. For ten points, name this Hungarian-born war photographer who took “The Falling Soldier.”",
        "answer": [
          "Robert Capa",
          "Endre Friedmann"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Another photograph that was accused of being posed was the iconic photograph of the raising of the flag on Mount Suribachi, which was taken by what photographer?",
        "answer": "Joseph Rosenthal"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Richard Rowland Kirkland saved numerous enemy soldiers in this battle. A sudden appearance of the aurora borealis occurred near the end of this battle. An offensive attempt after this battle turned into a disaster when heavy rains caused equipment to be stuck, earning it the nickname “Mud March.” Thousands of Union soldiers failed to capture positions on Marye’s Heights during this battle. Due to his failure in this battle, Ambrose Burnside was relieved of his command. For ten points, name this crushing defeat for the Union in December 1862 in Northern Virginia.",
        "answer": "Battle of Fredericksburg"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Confederate general commanded the successful defense at Marye’s Heights. At Gettysburg, he ordered the failed Pickett’s Charge, during which Union soldiers shouted “Give them Fredericksburg!”",
        "answer": "James Longstreet"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This complex houses the “throne of the immortal one,” or Akal Takht. Massa Ranghar profaned this structure by performing acts of gluttony and debauchery in it. Reginald Dyer commanded troops that committed a massacre near this structure in the Jallianwalla Bagh garden. This structure is located in a lake whose waters are known as the “pool of ambrosial nectar.” In 1984, two bodyguards disgruntled over the fact that this complex was targeted in Operation Blue Star assassinated Indira Gandhi. For ten points, name this gurdwara in Amritsar, the holiest site in Sikhism.",
        "answer": [
          "Golden Temple of Amritsar or Harmandir Sahib",
          "Darbar Sahib"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Golden Temple contains what original text written by Guru Arjan, which is regarded by Sikhs to be both the Sikh holy book and the last and everlasting guru?",
        "answer": "Adi Granth or Sri Guru Granth Sahib"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Kurt Muse was rescued during a raid on Carcel Modelo prison in this initiative, which secured Fort Amador and the “Bridge of the Americas.” This initiative called for the seizure of the El Chorillo neighboorhood, which was protected by Dignity Batallions. It led to the installment of Guillermo Endara after his predecessor was flushed out of the Vatican City embassy by loud music. Operation Just Cause was the codename of, for ten points, what US initiative that successfully deposed dictator Manuel Noriega from a certain Central American country?",
        "answer": [
          "Invasion of Panama",
          "Operation Just Cause before mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This elite unit of U.S. Army suffered the heaviest percentage of injuries in the invasion of Panama after heavy fighting at Rio Hato. Their motto is “lead the way.”",
        "answer": "U.S. Army Rangers"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One of this man’s final meals was with Mario Scaramella at the Itsu sushi bar. After this man’s death, a world leader ominously stated “[this man] is, unfortunately, not Lazarus.” This man’s final public statement was addressed to that world leader, telling him “silence comes at a price.” This man’s death was due to alpha radiation poisoning from a sample of polonium-210 that had been put in his tea by FSB agents, probably on the orders of Vladimir Putin. For ten points, name this Russian dissident who was killed in 2006.",
        "answer": "Alexander Litvinenko"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Litvinenko was poisoned two weeks after publicly accusing Putin of ordering the assassination of what other Russian human rights activist? She was shot in an elevator on Putin’s birthday in 2006.",
        "answer": "Anna Politkovskaya"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Three answers required. These three countries signed the London Straits Convention with the Ottoman Empire to ensure that their ships could safely pass through the Dardanelles. Two of these countries agreed to not trade with the third with the Treaty of Tilsit; for violating that agreement, one of those two countries was invaded in 1812. These three countries fought each other on opposite sides during the Crimean War. For ten points, name these three members of the Triple Entente in WWI.",
        "answer": [
          "United Kingdom, France, and Russia",
          "Great Britain",
          "England for UK"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Otto von Bismarck attempted to create what alliance of Germany, Austria-Hungary, and Russia in order to effectively control Eastern Europe?",
        "answer": "League of the Three Emperors"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man was defeated by his brother at Poenari Castle. Prince Basarab the Elder fled before this man, who was supported by the soldiers of Stephen Bathory. After sparking a conflict by refusing to pay the jizya, this man mistakenly targeted the tent of Ishak Pasha during his “Night Attack.” This member of the Order of the Dragon was opposed by his brother, Radu the Handsome, while attempting to defend his vovoideship from Ottoman invasion. For ten points, name this Wallachian ruler known for his method of disposing of foes on wooden stakes.",
        "answer": "Vlad the Impaler or Vlad III"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Vlad the Impaler joined this Hungarian ruler in a crusade against the Ottomans. This son of Janos [yahn-osh] Hunyadi formed the Black Army.",
        "answer": "Matthias Corvinus"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "MICHIGAN",
      "prompt": "In the history of Michigan, who or what was the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "neighboring state to the south against which it fought the Toledo War.",
          "answer": "Ohio"
        },
        {
          "question": "fort attacked during Pontiac’s War and namesake of its largest city.",
          "answer": "Fort Detroit"
        },
        {
          "question": "French missionary who established Sault Ste. Marie, noted for his work with Louis Jolliet.",
          "answer": "Jacques Marquette"
        },
        {
          "question": "controversial admissions policy over which the University of Michigan was sued in 2003’s Gratz v. Bollinger.",
          "answer": "affirmative action"
        },
        {
          "question": "Revolutionary British fort on a namesake island between Lakes Michigan and Huron.",
          "answer": "Fort Mackinac"
        },
        {
          "question": "1960s governor whose son lost the 2012 presidential election to Obama.",
          "answer": "George Romney"
        },
        {
          "question": "the high-traffic bridge connecting Detroit to Windsor, Ontario built after World War I.",
          "answer": "Ambassador Bridge"
        },
        {
          "question": "Democrat who earned the nickname “The Conscience of the Senate”.",
          "answer": "Phillip Aloysius Hart THE SWISS MILITARY"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "From the history of the Swiss military, identify the...",
      "prompt": "Name the from the history of the swiss military, identify the......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "city in which the Swiss Guard protects the Pope’s residence.",
          "answer": "Vatican City"
        },
        {
          "question": "1870 to 1871 was between Otto von Bismarck and Napoleon III during which Hans Herzog was Swiss General.",
          "answer": "Franco-Prussian War"
        },
        {
          "question": "treaty ending the Thirty Years War which first recognized Swiss independence, allowing neutrality.",
          "answer": "Peace of Westphalia"
        },
        {
          "question": "German air force from which the Swiss shot down 11 planes during World War II for air space violations.",
          "answer": "Luftwaffe"
        },
        {
          "question": "Swiss Reformation leader who led Protestants against Catholics in the Wars of Kappel.",
          "answer": "Huldrych Zwingli"
        },
        {
          "question": "country whose invading forces under Leopold III were defeated at the 1386 Battle of Sempach?",
          "answer": "Austria"
        },
        {
          "question": "planned Nazi invasion of Switzerland during World War II.",
          "answer": "Operation Tannenbaum"
        },
        {
          "question": "”special alliance” that fought a namesake civil war in 1847 against the rest of the Swiss federation.",
          "answer": "Sonderbund"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "THE WINTER OLYMPICS",
      "prompt": "In the history of the Winter Olympics, what...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "sport did the U.S. beat the U.S.S.R. in 1980’s “Miracle on Ice”?",
          "answer": "Men’s Ice Hockey"
        },
        {
          "question": "sport did Nancy Kerrigan compete in after her knee was clubbed in 1994?",
          "answer": "Women’s Figure Skating"
        },
        {
          "question": "sport did the Jamaicans inexplicably start competing in at the 1988 games in the 2- and 4-man varieties?",
          "answer": [
            "Bobsled",
            "Bobsleigh"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "only Asian nation to host a Winter Olympics, doing so in 1972 and 1998?",
          "answer": "Japan"
        },
        {
          "question": "city in upstate New York hosted the 1932 and 1980 Games?",
          "answer": "Lake Placid"
        },
        {
          "question": "sport did Eric Heiden win a record 5 gold medals in in 1980?",
          "answer": "Speed Skating"
        },
        {
          "question": "French city near the border with Switzerland and Italy hosted the inaugural 1924 Winter Olympics?",
          "answer": "Chamonix"
        },
        {
          "question": "country is the only one to boycott a Winter Games, doing so in 1980?",
          "answer": "Taiwan or Chinese Taipei"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The British sponsored a failed scheme to plant vast amounts of peanuts in this modern- day country to provide much-needed oil. A rebellion in this modern-day country that was crushed by Gustav Adolf von Gotzen was led by Kinjikitile (20 pts)",
        "Ngwale, who spread the belief that bullets would turn into water if warriors consumed a “war medicine” called maji. A colony encompassing the territory of this modern-day country was the target of the Allies in the (10 pts)",
        "East Africa Campaign, which managed to wrest it from German colonial control. For ten points, name this modern-day country whose territory was mostly comprised of the colony of Tanganyika."
      ],
      "answer": "Tanzania"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This composer’s namesake approach to music education made heavy use of xylophones. He falsely claimed to be a co-founder of the White Rose resistance movement during de-Nazification, but he did accept a Nazi commission to replace (20 pts)",
        "Mendelssohn’s work on A Midsummer Night’s Dream. He included “Blanzifor et Helena” in a cantata, the first part of Trionfi, whose texts were taken from a collection of medieval (10 pts)",
        "secular songs and which opens and closes with an ode to the title “whirling wheel” of fate. For ten points, name this composer, who wrote “O Fortuna” as part of his Carmina Burana."
      ],
      "answer": "Carl Orff"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Charles Grey ambushed this man’s forces in the Paoli Massacre. This man led a surprisingly successful bayonet raid on a British fort at Stony Point, after which he earned his nickname. He provokingly established Fort Recovery at the site of the Battle of the (20 pts)",
        "Wabash River. This leader of the Legion of the United States forced the Treaty of Greenville after his decisive victory over (10 pts)",
        "Little Turtle and Blue Jacket’s Miami tribe at the Battle of Fallen Timbers. The Northwest Indian War was essentially won by, for ten points, what American general, nicknamed “Mad?”"
      ],
      "answer": "”Mad” Anthony Wayne"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) At one battle at this site, duckboards were required on ground level and soldiers drowned in mud if they lost their balance; during that battle, one side took Menin Road and Polygon Wood. An attempt to capture this city during the (20 pts)",
        "Spring Offensive led Alexander Haig to issue the “Backs to the Wall” order. A corruption of this city’s name named a popular satirical trench newspaper that was popular among troops fighting in this city’s (10 pts)",
        "salient. For ten points, name this Flemish town that was the site of several bloody battles, including the first major use of poison gas, during World War I."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Ypres or Ieper",
        "or Wipers",
        "Passchendaele before “Spring” is read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Early in this work, one figure answers why “devil” and “snake” are used interchangeably in stories of the Garden of Eden. 60 Minutes’ Mike Wallace co-produced this work with Louis Lomax. In this work, an excerpt of a play called The Trial is shown in which the declaration “I charge the (20 pts)",
        "white man with being the greatest murderer on earth!” is given by Louis Farrakhan. Malcolm X rose in prominence after his interviews in this work were (10 pts)",
        "broadcast. For ten points, name this July 1959 five-part documentary about “the rise of Black Racism,” focusing on the Nation of Islam’s “gospel of hate.”"
      ],
      "answer": "The Hate that Hate Produced"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Shortly after the first of these events, Nelli Kim matched the feat three times. According to legend, Omega’s anticipation of this event was ignored by officials, who claimed that equipment with three (20 pts)",
        "digits would be suitable for use. Eight years after this event, Mary Lou Retton matched it under the tutelage of the same coach, Bela (10 pts)",
        "Karolyi. This event took place seven times at Montreal, beginning with the uneven bars. For ten points, name this flawless feat performed at the 1976 Summer Olympics by a certain Romanian gymnast."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Nadia Comaneci’s perfect 10s",
        "descriptions"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) These weapons were used in coordination with panokseon to win the Battles of Okpo and Myeongnyang for Yi Sun-Shin. Lennart Torstenson commanded these weapons effectively to thwart Count Tilly’s advance at (20 pts)",
        "Breitenfeld, and early heavy-usage of these these weapons doomed John Talbot at Castillon. Variants of these weapons included serpentines and culverins, and Orban introduced them to (10 pts)",
        "Mehmed II, allowing the capture of Constantinople. For ten points, name these weapons mounted on galleons and frigates, large guns that shot heavy stone and metal balls."
      ],
      "answer": "cannons"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Marco Sanudo ruled this island after it was conquered by the French during the Fourth Crusade. An early Bronze Age settlement on this island was at Phylakopi. People from this island are told “The strong (20 pts)",
        "do as they can, and the weak suffer what they must” in response to their refusal to submit to rule; shortly after, this island’s males are killed and the women and children sold into slavery by the Athenians. A famous artifact from this island was called “a big (10 pts)",
        "gendarme” by Renoir, and is believed to be by Alexandros of Antioch. For ten points, name this Greek island whose “dialogue” with Athens is recorded in Thucydides’ History of the Peloponnesian War, the discovery site of an armless statue of Venus."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Melos",
        "Milo",
        "Venus de Milo",
        "Melian dialogue"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One theory of the cause of this event was supported by a Antonio Camargo and Glen Penfield discovery. Luis Alvarez proposed one cause of this event, declaring that chondrites probably deposited the staggering level of (20 pts)",
        "iridium he found in shocked quartz in the crust. A decade later, the discovery of the (10 pts)",
        "Chicxulub [chick-shu-loob] crater bolstered that theory of this event. For ten points, name this devastating event that marks the boundary between two eras of geologic time and occurred roughly 66 million years ago."
      ],
      "answer": "Cretaceous-Tertiary extinction event"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One man took advantage of the high prevalence of handkerchiefs in this event, which made a rule about “open hands” unenforceable. James Parker unsuccessfully tried to stop this event, whose perpetrator said “I have (20 pts)",
        "done my duty” before being knocked out by rifle butts. After being inspired by Gaetano Bresci, one participant in this event managed to hide a (10 pts)",
        "gun under a bandage wrap. For ten points, name this 1901 event that took place at Buffalo’s Pan-American Exposition and resulted in Leon Czolgosz [zhul-gosh] being arrested for murder."
      ],
      "answer": "assassination of William McKinley"
    }
  ]
}